<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The Queys</title>
  <id>http://thequeys.com</id>
  <link href="http://thequeys.com"/>
  <link href="http://thequeys.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2025-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Rebekah and Ryan Quey</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>We Made It!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2025/06/25/june-update/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2025/06/25/june-update/</id>
    <published>2025-06-25T00:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2025-07-07T07:36:30+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_group align-center wrap"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/cohbc/caregroup_2024-92b65109.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/cohbc/manirumvas_2025-4df775e6.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/hyons_2025-5225b2e3.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/with_chos_2025-3c93c6aa.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/gomo_caregroup_2025-df96d31a.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/halmuni_2025-c0b0daaa.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/cousins_2025-1d7a5fe5.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/jason_anna_2024-1c8961b8.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic"&gt; Pictures from our time in the States with churches, family and friends&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it has been so good to see friends and family in the States for the last six months, it is wonderful to be back in Cambodia. We have been...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_group align-center wrap"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/cohbc/caregroup_2024-92b65109.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/cohbc/manirumvas_2025-4df775e6.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/hyons_2025-5225b2e3.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/with_chos_2025-3c93c6aa.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/gomo_caregroup_2025-df96d31a.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/halmuni_2025-c0b0daaa.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/cousins_2025-1d7a5fe5.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/furloughs/jason_anna_2024-1c8961b8.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic"&gt; Pictures from our time in the States with churches, family and friends&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though it has been so good to see friends and family in the States for the last six months, it is wonderful to be back in Cambodia. We have been here in country for about a month – one week in Phnom Penh running paperwork and getting over jet-lag, and the rest in our new home in the city of Banlung, Ratanakiri province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a lot to be thankful for already, and just wanted to share this with you all, that you may join us in exalting our great God for all that He does, big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="thank-the-lord-for-his-provision-with-our-children"&gt;Thank the Lord for His Provision with our Children&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been good to see the kids settling into the new city as well. Initially, to be honest we were somewhat concerned about this, especially due to passing comments made by the kids about how they will miss America, and then how much they will miss our old house, old friends, and old church in Phnom Penh. As left Phnom Penh early morning June 6th, it seemed like the more we talked about the importance of following the Lord’s calling, of trusting God’s protection and provision, and all of the things we had to look forward to in our new home in Ratanakiri, the more they talked about how much they will miss all of what we left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end though, it was us as parents who needed to trust God most of all, as He prepared their hearts. It’s hard to know exactly what goes on in the hearts of our children, but it seems that the breakthrough finally happened on the very first night we were here. As we setup our beds and mosquito nets, something caught the boys’ eye: a large beetle stuck to the netting, just a thin fabric’s width away from falling right on their pillows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way that only an eldest son can, Jonathan (the ring-leader of our motley crew) set the tone for the rest of the children, declaring: “I’m going to like it here, Ratanakiri has a lot of bugs.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praise God for the bugs. &lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/2025/big_bad_bug-5dda3f55.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/2025/anna_caterpillar2-e7c298e8.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/2025/anna_caterpillar-ac7ce0ea.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="thank-the-lord-for-his-guidance-over-his-church"&gt;Thank the Lord for His Guidance over His Church&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been wonderful joining in with the local congregation here in town. As we shared before, one of the pastors offered to rent out his house, which conveniently is about 100 yards away from the church building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have loved getting to know the saints here. Leading up to our original decision to move up here, the other missionaries had told us of the vibrancy and steadfastness of the faith of the local believers here, and this last month has only confirmed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous examples could be given here, but I wanted to share about one event in particular as an encouragement, as well as an answer to prayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big prayer requests we shared during our time in the States is for the Cambodian church to grow in internalizing and taking personal responsibility for their role in the Great Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can imagine how we felt then when, on our very first Sunday here, the pastor preached on Romans 15 and Paul’s heart to go to Spain. But the elders were not content to just talk about the importance of the church being involved in reaching the nations. The pastor then announced that the elders had come up with a plan for a group of eight (mostly pastors from this church and some &lt;a href="https://www.peoplegroups.org/explore/GroupDetails.aspx?peid=20437"&gt;Jarai&lt;/a&gt; churches in the next town over) to make an overnight trip to visit a national missionary, Pro-In, and his wife Si-Ma, in order to encourage them in their work among the Laotian people in Cambodia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you might remember Pro-In, from when we shared about Ratanakiri Province during our visit to the States. He and his wife are actually not ethnically Khmer - they are &lt;a href="https://joshuaproject.net/people_groups/11129/CB"&gt;Bunong&lt;/a&gt;, but among the first missionaries that any Cambodian church has sent out. Here then is a Khmer Church, partnering with some Jarai churches to encourage a Bunong missionary family in their efforts to reach the Laotians.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/labansiek/labansiek_visit_laotianchurch-f2bcb7fb.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/labansiek/visiting_laotianchurch-effce499.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/labansiek/visiting_laotianchurch2-6f778cd1.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We felt not unlike Rhoda and the church in Jerusalem - active in intercession for this very thing, yet full of surprise (to the point of incredulity) when God actually answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praise God for building His Church.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Missions and the Mundane</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2024/12/01/dec/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2024/12/01/dec/</id>
    <published>2024-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2025-07-06T22:51:51+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After our last update, we received some emails commenting on all number of the activities we are involved with, some also expressing some degree of concern. First of all - thank you to all who wrote, and for reaching out to us in that regard. We really...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After our last update, we received some emails commenting on all number of the activities we are involved with, some also expressing some degree of concern. First of all - thank you to all who wrote, and for reaching out to us in that regard. We really do appreciate the care that so many have expressed on our behalf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we did want to clarify one thing in particular. Perhaps because our newsletters are often only sent out once every 2-3 months, but we really are engaged with much less than it might appear. Furthermore, the pictures we post often highlight the &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt; over against the regular, unchanging, day-in day-out ministry that is more typical and characteristic of what our lives here consist of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might say, “Well why not put pictures that are more typical then?” The fact is, if we sent a picture of a more typical day in ministry, it would mostly look the same from week to week, month to month, and year to year: Ryan sitting at a desk, pouring over the Scriptures - or perhaps a picture of Rebekah, engaged in casual conversation over lunch with someone from church. However, for better or for worse, I am not apt to take pictures of myself sitting at my desk - hence why the pictures that end up in the newsletters tend to be more dynamic, and therefore less representative of our actual typical activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To which you might reply, “Well wouldn’t putting these pictures still be better? Isn’t accuracy and communicating a true picture of your ministry more valuable than exciting newsletters with fun pictures?” To which I would respond, that yes, that’s quite reasonable and well worth considering, and is perhaps a fault that should be corrected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I thought that it might be beneficial to write this brief clarification. My particular concern to clarify this comes in part so as to not misrepresent what we are doing here, but also particularly so as to not lead to any confusion about the nature of ministry and missions in general. In many ways, there is nothing “glorious” about missions. Relatively speaking, there is a lot more just sitting at a desk than there is being involved in flashly programs or campaigns, or traversing through the jungle searching for unreached tribal people groups - at least for most missionaries that I know of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I would want to emphasize that from another angle, it is in fact quite full of glory - though in many ways, it is a “veiled glory,” to borrow the language of the Apostle Paul (2 Cor 4:3). It is not a glory that would appeal instantly to us in our flesh. In fact, taking the Apostle Paul himself as an example, it is a glory that the world despises, and can only be viewed through the eyes of faith, as we look forward to our eternal reward on that last day when Christ Himself returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth emphasizing that it is a glory that all of us can participate in, in whatever continent we happen to be in, inasmuch as all of us can be engaged in the ministry of the New Covenant. I pray that all of us would be found faithful before Him on that day, as we look forward with eager anticipation to the glory still to be revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Finishing Strong</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2024/09/10/sept/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2024/09/10/sept/</id>
    <published>2024-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2025-06-25T21:06:14+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the next couple months we will be wrapping up our time at Phnom Penh Bible School, where Ryan has been teaching since we came back to Cambodia in 2021. Students who were in the first class that Ryan taught have all graduated already; students who...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the next couple months we will be wrapping up our time at Phnom Penh Bible School, where Ryan has been teaching since we came back to Cambodia in 2021. Students who were in the first class that Ryan taught have all graduated already; students who were just starting then are now getting ready to graduate and head off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/team/action-retreat/2024_action_retreat_zoom_garden_cafe_1-46f9f703.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/team/action-retreat/2024_action_retreat_zoom_garden_cafe_2-56d3e5b1.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align:center;font-style:italic"&gt;Pictures from our ACTION team retreat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praise God for all of the students who have invested long nights, tired mornings, and years of their lives in order to know God through His Word and be better prepared to serve Him in His Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please pray for the students as fourth year students are getting ready to graduate, and deciding how to spend their lives. Pray that they would lay down every ambition and turn away from every temptation for self-gain or promotion, and seek instead His Kingdom and His righteous. Pray for God’s provision as they head out to a Church that on the whole lacks well-designed internship programs, associate pastor positions, or for the most part any support or mentorship for them at all. Pray that they would be bold but humble, diligent but dependent, as they begin this next stage of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="some-praises-at-church"&gt;Some Praises at Church&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/church/rcc_retreatgroup2_2024-29d123fa.jpg" alt="" /&gt; On a church retreat with RCC, the presbyterian church that we regularly attend&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/church/chuchofmercy_2024-2c94bfd9.jpg" alt="" /&gt; We’ve visited Church of Mercy, a sound church in the province that also translates resources to Khmer, and are always encouraged by our time there.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lately there have been a string of encouragements, and reminders that God is still at work here in Cambodia and around the world. To be clear, these aren’t individuals whom we can claim any credit for their conversion (as if there were ever any), but we wanted to share this just as an encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been encouraged overall at our time with this church. It’s a little bit different for us worshiping at a Presbyterian church, but we have been encouraged more than ever about our unity in Christ that transcends all barriers (including denominational barriers)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="upcoming-furlough"&gt;Upcoming Furlough&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of November, we will be visiting the States in order to spend time and reconnect with our supporting churches, as well as to rest some before we launch off for Ratanakiri next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tentative Dates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arrive in Spokane on Nov 28th&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave Spokane for Seattle 2nd or 3rd week of February.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave Seattle early March. Visit friends in Oregon along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay around 1-1.5 weeks in the Bay Area&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arrive in LA end of March (around Mar 21st)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Somewhere in here, we want to try to visit family in Georgia.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Return to Cambodia end of May 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="encouragement-from-ppbs-students"&gt;Encouragement from PPBS Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we wrap up our time with PPBS, we thought we would share some encouragement from the students there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/pagnafamily_kny_2024-b3233c32.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Testimony from a recent graduate, Pagna (left) – pictured with his wife and our family for Khmer New Year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent graduate Pagna shared about &lt;em&gt;The Family Life of a Christian Leader&lt;/em&gt;, a book he read for the “Marriage and Family” course he took at PPBS. The book was translated last year by Plovpit (Action Cambodia’s translation team).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Family Life of a Christian Leader&lt;/em&gt; is a book that provides valuable insight into the unique challenges and blessings that come with being a Christian leader in the context of family life.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Scriptural Foundation: This book emphasizes the importance of strengthening family life in biblical principles, such as love, forgiveness, and mutual respect.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Practical Advice: This book provides practical advice and strategies for balancing the needs of leadership with the responsibilities of family life.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Practical Stories: The author shares personal stories and stories from other Christian leaders to illustrate the main points, will give me encouragement facing problems.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Spiritual Growth: This book helped me to explore how family life can be a motivating factor for spiritual growth and change for both Christian leaders and my family members.​&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/leang.thong/posts/pfbid0JLb8jDgTwXBuaH2tz7bHYKRJuYmWVNyLp7b1fvS2Rhkg2rehmmzRFtDNpkfwNaegl"&gt;see original&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more testimonies, you can see the PDF below. They invited me to share some about spiritual growth in the context of theological education as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://1drv.ms/b/s!AiKm233nOqajhY5hOonBe3AcUMtnhA?embed=1&amp;amp;em=2" width="90%" height="650" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id="prayer-requests"&gt;Prayer Requests&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is bittersweet as we plan to move to Ratanakiri. All of our time in Cambodia has been in Phnom Penh with our ACTION teammates and the Church here. There is a part of us that feels it will be difficult to be in a new place and new church family all over again, but we trust God’s plan and are very much excited to serving in Ratanakiri. Pray for wisdom as we navigate saying goodbyes and keeping up some relationships as well. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting ready for furlough – God’s guidance doing homeschool during furlough, visiting the Church and family; we pray our time would be fruitful and encouraging for brothers and sisters as well as non-believers we will be spending time with.&lt;br /&gt;
Especially for our children, who are getting older, as they think through differences between America and Cambodia, things they like, dislike, meeting many different people whom they are “supposed to” know (family, etc.), but still feeling distant, relationships, languages, having certain attractions or aversions to cultural differences etc. God’s wisdom for us as parents in this regard as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faithfulness each day with what God has put before us, trusting Him for every interaction, decision, and activity not knowing when the Master will call us home or what His plans for us are. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There have been a number of sick people in the hospital in the past few weeks, as well as a couple deaths - one, the sister of our helper, the other, a young 11-year-old boy who drowned in Ratanakiri (his parents are believers and part of the Jarai church, an ethnic minority). Pray that these opportunities would allow for the Gospel of Christ to shine through feelings of hopelessness and suffering. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id="bonus-life-happenings"&gt;Bonus Life Happenings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/us/fathersday_2024-dfafc8dd.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Father’s Day &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/team/ombirthday_2024-097c1457.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Our wonderful helper’s birthday&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/outside_pp/hancockchildren_2024-90b76662.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Visiting new teammates outside Phnom Penh&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/tamao_ponleu-36c0f00c.jpg" alt="" /&gt; A trip to the Zoo with PPBS students &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/tamao_monkey_soda-197d1ed1.jpg" alt="" /&gt; This zoo has TONS of wild monkeys, some of which are super bold and come very close to humans. This one snagged an abandoned soda. &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/pagnavisits_2024-57c3342b.jpg" alt="" /&gt; A PPBS student brings his family to our home for a visit&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/facultyretreat_2024-0c598361.jpg" alt="" /&gt; PPBS Faculty had a retreat to Sihanoukville&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/flood_boys_2024-6ddc55ce.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Rainfall on a particularly heavy day led to major flooding at the Bible School as well as many homes. These students are still very cheery! &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/flood_2024-abf896de.jpg" alt="" /&gt; The flood made PPBS look like a lake! Some people were actually fishing for dinner that day! &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/neighborhood/playingoutside_2024-78cf2b0b.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Out in our neighborhood &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/neighborhood/sophea_david_2024-73b86688.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Precious children in our neighborhood and our precious Samuel &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/church/shalommensg_2024-aba52d6a.jpg" alt="" /&gt; A small group Ryan has been part of for about 6 years recently ended&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Seeking to Be Found Faithful</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2024/06/05/june/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2024/06/05/june/</id>
    <published>2024-06-05T00:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2025-06-25T21:06:14+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/car_to_rtk_2024-064740ca.jpg" alt=""&gt; On the road to Ratanakiri (RTK) with Phnom Penh Bible School students for Pastors’ School&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_families_24-89925de9.jpg" alt=""&gt; After finishing Romans, the Pastors’ school taught on biblical families and marriages &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg "&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/teachers_24-480996df.jpg" alt=""&gt; Most of the teachers for the Pastors’ school in April (in RTK...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/car_to_rtk_2024-064740ca.jpg" alt="" /&gt; On the road to Ratanakiri (RTK) with Phnom Penh Bible School students for Pastors’ School&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_families_24-89925de9.jpg" alt="" /&gt; After finishing Romans, the Pastors’ school taught on biblical families and marriages &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg "&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/teachers_24-480996df.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Most of the teachers for the Pastors’ school in April (in RTK) &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As the semester draws to a close, it provides a good opportunity for reflection. This upcoming semester will, Lord willing, be my last at the Phnom Penh Bible School (PPBS). I have been teaching at PPBS for over 3 years now (as of March), and it will be bittersweet moving on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are however looking forward to what’s next. Lord willing we will be joining a team in Ratanakiri Province to do theological education among the pastors up there, most of whom are part of ethnic minority tribes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One part of this that we are looking forward to, is the team dynamic, particularly the opportunity to learn from the experience of the veteran missionaries up there. We have benefited immensely from the team here in Phnom Penh, and we are sure that we will gain from the men and women up there also, as we have learned so much from them already even from our brief interactions that we have had thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="april-2024-training"&gt;April 2024 Training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to also give a quick report from the training that they put on in April. Thank you again for all of your prayers, the feedback has been very positive. The topic for the training was on the family Life of a Christian leader, and it seemed like this was particularly timely for the pastors and their wives and the church here overall. &lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/booktable_julia_24-b836d6f3.jpg" alt="" /&gt; A missionary friend’s daughter running the book table – selling lots of books from Plovpit (our translation team’s biblical resources) and more!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Christians here are still first generation Christians, and one side effect of not having grown up in Christian homes is a lack of examples to follow. Many believers (including pastors and their wives) want to conduct their marriage and raise their children in a biblical manner, but lack good role models to look up to as well as training in regard to God’s plan for the family. Of course one does not have to grow up into a Christian family in order to see good role models, particularly when there are other families in the church that one can look to and learn from. However, when all of the other families in the church including the pastor is in the same boat as yourself, then it can be difficult to know whom to look to for help. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_group_24-c6079cbd.jpg" alt="" /&gt; The whole group&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_ryan_24-6bd7f58d.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Ryan teaching on the importance of children obeying their parents &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container sm"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_jd_24-efca7fe7.jpg" alt="" /&gt; JD Crowley, who started the Pastors’ school, has served 30+ years in Cambodia &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_families2_24.jpg" alt="" /&gt; We are praying the teaching will impact the hearts of many of these families &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/familytraining_children_24-1ba8352e.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Some child care was also provided that allowed wives to join the sessions &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please pray for continued grace in this respect for the pastors and churches of Cambodia, and that they would build a firm foundation for future generations of Christians in Cambodia to follow after. Pray for &lt;strong&gt;husbands&lt;/strong&gt; as they seek to love their wives as Christ loves the Church, and for &lt;strong&gt;wives&lt;/strong&gt; as they submit and support their husbands as the Church to Christ. Pray for &lt;strong&gt;parents&lt;/strong&gt; to train up their children in the training and admonition of the Lord, and particularly for &lt;strong&gt;fathers&lt;/strong&gt; that they would take responsibility for the discipleship of their household. Pray also for the many &lt;strong&gt;mothers&lt;/strong&gt; whose husband does not yet know Christ, but are seeking to raise their children in the Lord on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenges are great and many, and in many ways it feels like an uphill battle - indeed humanly speaking, the obstacles are insurmountable. So many biblical principles for parenting are incredibly countercultural, and the pastors were discussing how often their neighbors would mock them for trying to live biblically - for example, for men in the family to help with household chores or show affection to their wives. However, we know that greater is He that is in us than he that is in the world, and we have great hope for the future of the Church here. We must not underestimate what it means to have the Holy Spirit of God himself dwelling in each of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the same line, pray for the &lt;strong&gt;children&lt;/strong&gt;, that even now the Lord would be raising up future Leaders of the church among the boys and girls of today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous trainings, mostly only the men participated, however this time due to the nature of the topic, their wives were all so invited and some child-care was also provided. This being the case, it was the first time meeting many of the pastor’s wives and children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, there are definitely great challenges that still need to be overcome, but there are also very many encouraging signs of lives and families being transformed by the gospel. One evening in particular, we were sitting at the back of the church drinking tea and winding down for the night, and got to hear a very encouraging testimony of how some of the pastors were already making a difference in their village by the light of Christ shown through their lives. They shared about how when they first started trying to apply God’s plan for the family in their own lives, their neighbors would make fun of them, for example calling the men weak and emasculated for treating their wives with respect and dignity. However, as time went on and their godly lives bore fruit which showed itself in their families, their neighbors started to take notice, and wanted to learn how to do it themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pray for the light of Christ to continue to shine in the neighborhoods and villages of Cambodia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, two of the students from PPBS also came with me from Phnom Penh. Although there are no end to the number of trainings that go on in Phnom Penh, the students recognized that there is something different and special about the trainings that they have in Ratanakiri. For one student, Ponleu, this is his second time joining in on the training in Ratanakiri. He isn’t married yet, but wants to know what the Bible has to say about Christian families so that he is ready for the future. Another student and his wife also came along with their 2 year old daughter. It is a 9 hour trek up one way, but all of us gained from going and there are no regrets!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please pray for the families (current and future) of these PPBS students as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/sg24_ra_nita-30d68f22.jpg" alt="" /&gt; A couple from the province who came to study at the Bible school&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/ryan_sg_women_24-01ecc33e.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Ryan’s small group at the Bible school went out for dinner together!&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/us/samuel_bike_2024-dd3ddde8.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Enjoying time in our neighborhood while we still can &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/church/church_road_24-16c0e5d5.jpg" alt="" /&gt; After church with 14-cent ice cream! &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/church/childrensday3_kimlong-d1fd6d7e.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Spending time with PPBS alumni for International Childrens’ Day&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teaching and Equipping</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2024/04/12/first-quarter-2024/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2024/04/12/first-quarter-2024/</id>
    <published>2024-04-12T00:00:00-07:00</published>
    <updated>2025-06-25T21:06:14+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h1 id="the-last-few-months"&gt;The Last Few Months&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="short-training-in-steung-treng"&gt;Short Training in Steung Treng&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/SteungT/road_to_st_24-eecf21b2.jpg" alt=""&gt; On the road to Steung Treng&lt;/span&gt;Last February we had the opportunity to go visit Steung Treng, the province right next to Ratanakiri. Ryan was invited to teach on Ezra-Nehemiah, and Esther (right now...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id="the-last-few-months"&gt;The Last Few Months&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="short-training-in-steung-treng"&gt;Short Training in Steung Treng&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/SteungT/road_to_st_24-eecf21b2.jpg" alt="" /&gt; On the road to Steung Treng&lt;/span&gt;Last February we had the opportunity to go visit Steung Treng, the province right next to Ratanakiri. Ryan was invited to teach on Ezra-Nehemiah, and Esther (right now they’re doing Old Testament survey).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is similar to the school in Ratanakiri (originally purposed for pastors, but they allow women and other interested persons to join) just at an earlier stage. The size of the training is about the same too (60-65 students or so), but it’s different in that they do it once a month for one day rather than twice a year for 4-5 days. Perhaps this might turn into something that we are able to participate in regularly when we move up to Ratanakiri next year as well - right now it’s a bit far but it will be much closer to us when we go to Ratanakiri in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container xl center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/SteungT/training_24-12bcde52.jpg" alt="" /&gt; The group that joined for this training&lt;/span&gt;As an aside, please thank the Lord with us, for the generosity of those who gave so generously that we could have a car. We haven’t had a need for it for our first five years in Cambodia, but now with four kids it’s been a great blessing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially helpful for getting around to other provinces in Cambodia, for example for the training this last February to Steung Treng and then for this upcoming training in Banlung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="teaching-at-ppbs"&gt;Teaching at PPBS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_sg-574588f1.jpg" alt="Ryan's Small Group at PPBS" /&gt; Ryan’s Small Group at PPBS &lt;/span&gt;Ministry at PPBS continues. Ryan is still teaching Beginning Hebrew and the book of Isaiah. Everytime we read through Isaiah, we always see more and more of God’s glory in salvation as He works out His plan of Salvation through His Servant, the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="visiting-kampong-chhnang"&gt;Visiting Kampong Chhnang&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One special event that came up in the last few weeks was a short Field Ministry trip to Kampong Chhnang province. It was a great time of learning and hands-on discipleship as we talked about ministry, sharing the gospel, and what God’s heart is for Christ’s Bride, the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One particular encouragement came when it came time to do visitation and gospel sharing among the neighbors. From the Pastor’s experience, the neighborhood where students were going is particularly resistant to the gospel, and he even recommended that it might be best just to go and talk and mention we’re Christians, but not share the gospel outright. For many of us - admittedly, too often, myself included! - this would be enough of an excuse to take the easy road of least resistance and do just that. However, we talked and prayed about it the night before the students were going to go out, in particular discussing Acts 5 and the example of the Apostles, in how they demonstrate in their actions the importance of the gospel which compels us to share it with others. When the Jewish leaders forbade them from preaching the gospel of Christ, Peter and the apostles answered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We must obey God rather than men. The God of our fathers raised Jesus, whom you killed by hanging him on a tree. God exalted him at his right hand as Leader and Savior, to give repentance to Israel and forgiveness of sins. And we are witnesses to these things, and so is the Holy Spirit, whom God has given to those who obey him.” (Acts 5:29–32)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s striking how they don’t just refuse to obey, they even go on and preach the gospel right there to the High Priest and the Sanhedrin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were talking, one student in particular took a hard stand - for him, his conscience wouldn’t allow him to just go and visit the village without sharing the gospel as well. We knew clearly that no one there had ever heard the gospel before, and that this might be one of the few chances they ever would. Other students expressed agreement, and we all prayed together for help and wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they went out the next morning, the students were excited to share the gospel. In God’s providence, it went forward without any incident, and many heard the Gospel of Jesus Christ that day for the first time. Pray that the seeds planted would bear fruit in many lives. Pray also for these students, whose convictions are being shaped now, and that they would continue to walk in the Spirit and not quench His guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container lg center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_group_pdara-bf15d8af.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Children’s outreach with Pastor Dara&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_home_visits_prayer-8842c9e5.jpg" alt="" /&gt; The students visiting families in the neighborhood &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_home_visits-e010d39d.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Neighborhood visits&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_pagna-b54d2e51.jpg" alt="" /&gt; One of the students teaching &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container med"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_sg_pdara-e019b5ad.jpg" alt="" /&gt; With the pastor there, Pastor Dara, who is a PPBS alumnus &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container xl center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/field_ministry_24_setup-8e22fa27.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Set up at a church they visited on the trip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="upcoming-training-in-banlung-on-the-family"&gt;Upcoming Training in Banlung on the Family&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 16th, I (Ryan) will be going up for the last training in Ratanakiri before we move there Lord willing next year in 2025. This one will be particularly special, because it is focusing on the family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on in my time in Cambodia, I was a little bit disappointed on how much training and conferences there were about “application”, when were fundamental issues such as the nature of the gospel, God’s overall plan for redemptive history, and other fundamental biblical issues were still missing. Application of course is very necessary - without it we are just “hearing” without “doing”. The problem is just when trainings focus just on the “what” (ie methods) &lt;em&gt;to the exclusion&lt;/em&gt; of the “why” and the “how” (ie, the gospel core, our new hearts created anew in the New Covenant, by the power of the Holy Spirit, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when done properly, discussing the family is a very strategic opportunity for pastors and church members to really think about how the gospel changes everything in our lives. This kind of topic literally gets “in your kitchen”, forcing all of us to really ask ourselves if we are living in step with the gospel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/RTK_school_2023_group-37c1509c.jpg" alt="" /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;It is a very strategic topic as well for helping local churches - it is no accident that the apostle Paul mentions how one cannot possibly know how to manage the household of God without knowing how to manage his own household first (cf. 1 Tim 3). Particularly as the Cambodian Church is transitioning from being a first generation to a second generation church, this topic is particularly relevant in order to safeguard the future of churches here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please pray that there would not just be families with changed habits, but most of all that these changed habits would come about from changed hearts and renewed minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One prayer request in particular:&lt;/strong&gt; Pray for lasting fruit and for many of these pastors and teachers as they head back into their respective churches and ministries. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="image_container center"&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container sm"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/family_life_fernando-a73b8a36.jpg" alt="" /&gt; The book they will be using for this Pastor school session (although a bit edited)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="image_container sm"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/family_life_fernando_rtk-87b1484a.jpg" alt="" /&gt; This was translated into Khmer by the ACTION Cambodia translation team!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container sm"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/family_life_fernando_rtk2-c2f27d24.jpg" alt="" /&gt; These were brought to the pastors and attendees of the previous Pastor’s school in Ratanakiri&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="prayer-requests"&gt;Prayer Requests&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/sg_dinner_girls_kbbq-1664b4e8.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Students from PPBS came over for dinner together&lt;/span&gt; Besides the above prayer requests, please pray also for the following situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To finish strong at the Phnom Penh Bible School. Particularly that I would take advantage of the opportunities given to clearly articulate how the meaning of the gospel in the Old and New Testaments, and how it shapes how we do ministry in the church and in our lives today.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For our personal holiness, that we would be filled with the Holy Spirit and walk in Him more and more everyday.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For our children, that they’d be protected from temptation and most of all for their regeneration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For wisdom on our part, that we would raise our children in the training and admonition of the Lord.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For His glory,&lt;br /&gt;
Ryan and Rebekah&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Encouraged in the Lord</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://thequeys.com/2023/12/20/trip-to-steung-treng-and-rtk/"/>
    <id>http://thequeys.com/2023/12/20/trip-to-steung-treng-and-rtk/</id>
    <published>2023-12-20T00:00:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2025-07-06T22:59:45+07:00</updated>
    <summary type="html">
&lt;h1 id="what-weve-been-up-to"&gt;What we’ve been up to&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sharing-at-ppbs-missions-class"&gt;Sharing at PPBS Missions Class&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/yearend_party-1ce353de.jpg" alt="Year-end party in the classroom"&gt; Year-end party in the classroom&lt;/span&gt;One thing Pastor Abraham* shared in class that struck us all was the experience of Christians from the country he is going to, when he brought them to visit Cambodia...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">
&lt;h1 id="what-weve-been-up-to"&gt;What we’ve been up to&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sharing-at-ppbs-missions-class"&gt;Sharing at PPBS Missions Class&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/yearend_party-1ce353de.jpg" alt="Year-end party in the classroom" /&gt; Year-end party in the classroom&lt;/span&gt;One thing Pastor Abraham* shared in class that struck us all was the experience of Christians from the country he is going to, when he brought them to visit Cambodia. He shared that they were very excited and encouraged to be able to join with these Christians in worshiping openly, and were overcome with joy to see Bible schools and other institutions that we take for granted in places where there is religious freedom. On the other hand, they also felt some sadness that they aren’t able to worship like that themselves, in their own homeland. This struck a nerve with many of the PPBS students, as all of us realized what we have but only rarely give thanks to God for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praise God for Pastor Abraham’s heart for the lost and for Christ’s glory to be displayed among the nations, and pray that others like him would be raised up among the Church, both to hold the rope and to go down into the well, despite the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="missions-to-nearby-country"&gt;Missions to Nearby Country&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after he presented, we got ready to board the bus and head out to the country where Pastor Abraham* plans to serve full-time starting in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, despite our preparations, as it turned out at the last minute Ryan came down with a fever and was unable to join for the initial part of the trip, which was to a nearby SE Asian country. It was a difficult decision to make, but after discussing with other members of the team, it seemed best to all that it would be better for Ryan to stay home and try to rest so he might join in the latter part of the trip, and avoid getting the rest of the group sick in the meantime. As always though, we trust in God’s good providence and that He has a plan for this as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we were encouraged by what we heard and hope to be able to make trips to visit this pastor who is going to work there long-term starting in 2024. Please continue to pray for him, as he is making preparations full-time right now. Hopefully we will be able to visit him and his family in the future as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="nearby-se-asian-country---border-province"&gt;Nearby SE Asian Country -&amp;gt; Border Province&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan met Sok* (the Bible school student who was on the trip) when they came back in Cambodia however, and then headed over to meet a missionary working in the area. This missionary is also working with a people group from that same closed country, that are largely unreached in Cambodia. Although it would be difficult to share the gospel with this people group in their own country, it is a wide open field here in Cambodia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being the case, we were doubly surprised to hear that theirs is the only church they know of working with this people group in Cambodia, and they are fairly new at it. Nevertheless, praise God for great news, that they had their first five baptisms recently. We are reminded of Christ’s Word, “the harvest is plentiful but the workers are few” - please join us in praying for more harvesters to be sent out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to share more about this work in the future as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="border-province---banlung"&gt;Border Province -&amp;gt; Banlung&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/RTK_school_2023_2-e032c767.jpg" alt="" /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;From there we made our way to Banlung City, in Ratanakiri province, where our teaching is. This is the town where Rebekah and I plan to move in about a year and a half. We had a great time going through Romans 12-16 together, considering how the gospel truths of ch. 1-11 renew our minds and transform our lives, so that we can live “pleasing to Him”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a blessed time in many ways. Last time, we came to Ratanakiri as a family and for the most part spent time with the other missionaries (it was our first time meeting all of them). This time, Sok and I stayed at the church where the training was held and were able to spend much more time with the visiting pastors as well as the brothers from the host church, who had us over for multiple meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/students/sol_fait-efc1f43d.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Student who shared his thankfulness for the trainings&lt;/span&gt;One conversation in particular struck me. I almost cried for joy hearing him share from his heart how much he just loves coming to these trainings. He has a hard time with some of the more in-depth theological topics and intepretational issues we cover (for him, Khmer is his 2nd language since he is ethnically Jarai), but he soaks up everything he can get. Even more than that, he loves the fellowship with the brothers there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These trainings has been going on for almost as long as I have been alive, and for many of the pastors it is the only time they see each other. Because of this, they are often staying up quite late at night - some of those attending know this in advance and opt to stay in a guesthouse rather than staying at the church where the training is hosted, since otherwise they find they don’t get enough sleep at night to pay attention to the next day’s training! Which approach is better I cannot say, but for this particular brother, it’s one of his favorite parts - if you have ever been to a Shepherd’s Conference in the States (I’m sure other conferences are much the same way) it’s maybe the closest analogy I can think of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/RTK_school_2023_group-37c1509c.jpg" alt="" /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ratanakiri/pastor-school/ryan_teaching_2023-c0fc847d.jpg" alt="" /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pray for lasting fruit and for many of these pastors and teachers as they head back into their respective churches and ministries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="other-thanksgivings"&gt;Other Thanksgivings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We were so grateful to receive a care package from Anchor Bible Church in California! Thank the Lord with us for their love for us and their constant fellowship with us in His work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/abc/jonathan_ornament_carepackage-e88d1d83.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Jonathan and his favorite ornament from ABC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/abc/neighborhood_kids_christmas-f32309c1.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Neighborhood kids helping decorate for Christmas with little gifts from ABC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/abc/samuel_ornament_carepackage-4dc4a581.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Samuel and his favorite ornament from ABC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/abc/kids_books_carepackage-9f0391d8.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Thoughtful gifts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="image_container med center"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/sending_churches/abc/ryan_wedding_ring_carepackage-c2397659.jpg" alt="" /&gt; ABC sent us a replacement wedding ring for Ryan after he lost his; very grateful!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="prayer-requests"&gt;Prayer Requests&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/ppbs/newyear_2023-3a2ee83f.jpg" alt="" /&gt; Phnom Penh Bible School kicking off the new school year&lt;/span&gt; Besides the above prayer requests, please pray also for the following situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are continuing to confirm plans for the work in Ratanakiri starting early 2025 as well as other logistical/ministry details. Thank you for your continued prayer for this developing partnership for the gospel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pray for the students at PPBS that they would desire to know Christ through His Word, by the power of the Holy Spirit, and not get distracted by lesser pursuits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One concern has been seeing some indications of a lack of clarity in regard to some key gospel truths in students’ lives. Of course, all of us need these reminders about fundamental gospel realities - but just to say, pray for more opportunities to point students back to the gospel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg right"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/team/plovpit/plovpit.cambodia-translation-banner-6983b2c0.jpg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="giving-opportunity-plovpit-and-action-translation-team"&gt;Giving Opportunity: Plovpit and Action Translation Team&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently reminded of the importance of having valuable resources at the training in Ratanakiri. Our team member Jeff came up to join me and learn more about what the training is like. When he was introduced as being part of the team from “Plovpit” (Khmer for “true way”, which is our website’s name), several of the pastors came up to him and thanked him profusely for his work. He tried to tell them he was just part of the marketing team, but that didn’t slow them down at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As pastors serving in a country starving for theological resources and tools to help them understand the holy Scriptures, they know more than most the value of having books and articles in their own language, which can help them think through difficult shepherding and interpretational issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of Iain Murray’s comment, on why Scotland has had such an outsized impact for the Kingdom relative to its small size:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Foremost among the reasons has to be the recovery of biblical truth, and the persecution that followed, but scarcely less significant was the accompanying literature that moulded successive generations. Books were read, treasured, and then, as their owners approached their closing years, handed on to others. Titles received in this way constituted &lt;em&gt;something of a sacred trust&lt;/em&gt;, and that trust came to some of us when we were young” &lt;br /&gt;
(Murray, &lt;em&gt;A Scottish Christian Heritage&lt;/em&gt;, ix. Emph. added).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="image_container lg left"&gt;&lt;img src="../../../../images/cambodia/team/translation-team-completed-works-ecd851a1.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Please pray for a similar impact in the hearts and minds of Christian men and women here in Cambodia as well, as more resources become available. Pray that the distractions and snares of the world would not choke out the affections of believers here, and that the resources being produced now would bear fruit in generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation wing of Action Cambodia is raising money for various projects. &lt;a href="http://www.actioninternational.org/campaign/5657/CambodiaBooks2024"&gt;You can find more information in the links here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are also trying to take some of my lectures from PPBS and turn them into books that can be used within the church and within the classroom. Nathan Wells wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We desire to publish a comprehensive Bible commentary series in Khmer, transforming our teammate Ryan Quey’s Bible lectures from Phnom Penh Bible school into commentaries for pastors and students.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Your support will make these vital resources available to Khmer-speaking believers, fostering spiritual development in the Cambodian Church. Join our mission to enrich biblical understanding through the Cambodian Biblical Exposition Series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.actioninternational.org/campaign/340/cambodian-biblical-exposition-series"&gt;You can learn more here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation team was also featured in some recent interviews, you can see more here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xQNEo0natp4?si=2ECld7V1xRPvCaUX" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For His glory,&lt;br /&gt;
Ryan and Rebekah&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; Name changed for privacy reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
